Tufts Veterinary Medicine UP214
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Veterinary Medicine
1999 -- 2018
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine
UP214
0.5 Linear Feet
261 Megabytes
28 Digital Object(s)
This collection contains issues of Tufts Veterinary Medicine, published by the Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine, Tufts University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically ino one series.
Biographical / Historical
The School of Veterinary Medicine was established in 1978, opened in 1979, and graduated its first class in 1983. Established through the advocacy of President Jean Mayer, the school was unique in its affiliation to a health sciences complex rather than to a school of agriculture. The school is located on a 634 acre campus in Grafton, Massachusetts, site of a former state mental hospital. The school also shares facilities with the medical and dental schools on the downtown Boston campus, where vet students receive their first year of instruction in the basic sciences. Students at the veterinary school are exposed to care of all types of animals including food (cattle, sheep, swine, goat), fiber (sheep, llama), companion (dog, cat), and sporting (horse) animals. In addition, students are given the option of learning about care for wildlife through the wildlife medicine program. In addition to medicine, surgery, preventive medicine, and public health, the school also educates students about ethics, conservation medicine, and human-animal relationships.
Initial discussions on the establishment of a veterinary school were begun in the early 1970s as the absence of such a school in the New England region combined with a prediction of a nationwide deficit of veterinarians made the need apparent. After a variety of options were explored, including locating a school at the Otis Air Force base on Cape Cod, Tufts, under Jean Mayer's leadership, stepped forward to take the lead in the project. Richard B. Talbot, dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University was brought in as interim dean to oversee the startup of the school on a part-time basis. On April 29, 1978, the trustees voted to establish the school as part of Mayer's vision of an integrated "one medicine" program embracing the totality of medical, dental, veterinary, and nutrition education.
The school provides clinical facilities as part of the Tufts-New England Veterinary Medical Center, which includes the Foster Hospital for Small Animals, the Large Animal Hospital, the Cornelius Thibeault Equine Clinic, the Amelia Peabody Pavilion, the Issam Fares Equine Sports Medicine Program, the Harrington Oncology Program, and the Wildlife Clinic at Grafton, as well as the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, and the Ambulatory Farm Clinic based at Woodstock, Connecticut.
The degree of Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (D.V.M.) is the primary degree offered by the school, though since 1995 the school also offers a Master of Science (M.S.) in Animals and Public Policy. The school features several signature programs which offer specialized perspectives on veterinary sciences, including Wildlife Medicine, Equine Sports Medicine, International Veterinary Medicine, Ethics and Values in Veterinary Medicine, and Biotechnology and Veterinary Medicine.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the newsletter which has information about the School of Veterinary Medicine, and is geared toward alumni. In 2014, the Tufts Veterinary Medicine magazine changed its name to the Cummings Veterinary Medicine to celebrate the 10th anniversary of the schools relationship with the Cummings Foundation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Digitized copies of Tufts Veterinary News dating from 1999 -- 2004 were transferred by the Webster Family Library, 2019, accession UA-2020-014.
Alumni and Alumni Relations
- Tufts Veterinary Medicine, 1999 -- 2018; UP214.001; 0.25 Linear Feet; 13 Digital Object(s); 178.8 Megabytes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the Tufts Veterinary Medicine newsletter. It is geared toward alumni.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 1999 -- 2000; UP214.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Volume, issue
    1, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2000; UP214.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    1, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2000; UP214.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    1, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2001; UP214.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    2, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2001; UP214.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    2, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2001; UP214.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    2, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2001; UP214.000044
    3, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2002; UP214.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    3, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2002; UP214.000045
    4, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2002; UP214.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    4, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2003; UP214.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
    4, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2003; UP214.000046
    5, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2003; UP214.000047
    5, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2003; UP214.000048
    5, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2004; UP214.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
    6, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2004; UP214.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
    6, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2005; UP214.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
    6, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2005; UP214.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
    7, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2005; UP214.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
    7, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2006; UP214.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
    7, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2006; UP214.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
    8, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2006; UP214.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
    8, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2007; UP214.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
    8, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2007; UP214.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
    9, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, 2006 -- 2008; UP214.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
    (Summer 2006) through Vol 9, No 3 (Spring 2008)
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2008; UP214.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
    Second copy in bound volume in Reading Room.
    10, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2008; UP214.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
    10, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2009; UP214.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
    10, 3
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Fall 2009; UP214.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
    11, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2010; UP214.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
    11, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2010; UP214.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
    12, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2011; UP214.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
    12, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Fall 2011; UP214.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
    13, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2012; UP214.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
    13, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2013; UP214.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
    14, 2
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2013; UP214.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
    14, 1
  - Tufts Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2014; UP214.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
    15, 1
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2014; UP214.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
    15, 2
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2015; UP214.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
    16, 1
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Summer 2015; UP214.001.001.00035 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    16, 2
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Winter 2016; UP214.001.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, 6, 9, 84, Folder 1, Box 2)
    Volume, Number
    17, 1
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Fall 2016; UP214.001.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, 6, 9, 84, Folder 2, Box 2)
    17, 2
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2017; UP214.001.00001; 1 Digital Object(s)
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Fall 2017; UP214.001.00002; 1 Digital Object(s)
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Spring 2018; UP214.001.00003; 1 Digital Object(s) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cummings Veterinary Medicine, Fall 2018; UP214.001.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, 6, 9, 84, Folder 3, Box 2)
    19, 2